<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>php on Alejandro AO - Coding Knowledge Base</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/tags/php/</link><description>Recent content in php on Alejandro AO - Coding Knowledge Base</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aavila0707.github.io/tags/php/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The foreach loop in PHP</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/php/05-foreach-loop-php/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/php/05-foreach-loop-php/</guid><description>Arrays are probably one of the structures that you will work the most with. They exist for one main reason: to be able to iterate through their elements and perform operations with them. And the easiest way to iterate through arrays in PHP is using the foreach loop.
The syntax foreach loops look like similar to functions in their declaration method. Here is the syntax:
$states = [&amp;#39;Alabama&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Texas&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;California&amp;#39;]; foreach ($states as $state) { echo $state; } Foreach loops take every single element in your array and perform the same operation on them.</description></item><item><title>How to interact with the Wordpress database (WPDB)</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/10-wp-db/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/10-wp-db/</guid><description>I started working with Wordpress at a professional level only after I had already experimented with other stacks like MERN. I remember that at the beginning I used to feel quite constrained by the apparent lack of flexibility of the Wordpress framework.
Soon, I realised that actually Wordpress is way more complex and flexible than just creating simple blogs from prebuilt themes.
One of the things that I missed the most was the ability to manipulate the database with MongoDB.</description></item><item><title>Variables, constants and data types in PHP</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/php/04-data-types-in-php/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/php/04-data-types-in-php/</guid><description>Variables and constants in PHP are preceded by the dollar sign $. Convention dictates that you should define your constants with uppercase and your variables with camelCase. Here is how you declare variables and constants :
// to create a variable $myVariable = 23; // this assigns the value 23 to your variable // to create a constant define(&amp;#34;MY_CONSTANT&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;This is the value of my constant&amp;#34;); With constants, there is a third parameter that takes a boolean value to set if your constant is case-sensitive or not.</description></item><item><title>How to install PHP in your local computer</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/php/03-how-to-install-php/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/php/03-how-to-install-php/</guid><description>As we mentioned before, PHP is a server-side language. This means that it is made to run in a server and not in a local computer. So, in order to run it in your local computer, you need to simulate a server at home.
This is extremely easy. There are several softwares that allow you to run PHP locally. The one that I would recommend for beginners is MAMP (you can also install LAMP if you&amp;rsquo;re using Linux).</description></item><item><title>How to do Ajax in Wordpress</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/09-wp-ajax/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/09-wp-ajax/</guid><description>Sometimes we refer to AJAX in somewhat underestimating terms. Since it is everywhere, sometimes beginner programmers see it as a simple technology that should not be too complicated to use.
That is absolutely not true. AJAX can be extremely complicated for beginners since it involves both front and back-end technologies working together in a particular way. In this tutorial I will teach you how to do AJAX in Wordpress considering you are a beginner familiar with Javascript and PHP.</description></item><item><title>What is a server-side language?</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/php/02-what-is-a-server-side-language/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/php/02-what-is-a-server-side-language/</guid><description>To understand what it means when you say that a language is &amp;ldquo;server-side&amp;rdquo;, we first need to understand that there are two places where your code can be compiled in web development: client-side and server-side.
Client-side languages The first type of programming languages for the web are client-side programming languages. This means that they run on the browser of the people visiting our website (a.k.a. the client). In other words, let&amp;rsquo;s say you put your website code in your server and someone wants to visit your website.</description></item><item><title>How to register Wordpress menus</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/08-menus/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/08-menus/</guid><description>In this article we are going to answer the following question: how to register a menu in Wordpress?
If you are used to web development, you will have already worked with hard-coded menus. That is, the only way to update the elements in your menu is through your code.
Wordpress Admin, on the other hand, allows you to manage the elements of the menus that you can place in different parts of your website.</description></item><item><title>Why should I learn PHP?</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/php/01-why-learn-php/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/php/01-why-learn-php/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s talk about PHP. More precisely, why it is a language that every web developer should know and what makes it so important.
Even though there is a huge amount of people that hate it or dislike it (myself included in the latter category) it is noble to recognise its importance. After all, it powers nearly 80% of all websites on the internet. Not so insignificant after all, right?
What is special about PHP ?</description></item><item><title>How to create a custom plugin in Wordpress</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/07-custom-plugin-copy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/07-custom-plugin-copy/</guid><description>Learning how to create Wordpress plugins from scratch is an essential part of Wordpress development. Here we see how to use PHP to code a plugin in wht Wordpress framwork.
What is a plugin In short, a plugin is just an extension of the functionalities of Wordpress. It can contain any functions that will run at any specified point in the Wordpress cycle.
There is a main idea behind developing plugins to adapt your website to your needs.</description></item><item><title>Custom Post Types and Taxonomies in Wordpress</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/06-cpt/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/06-cpt/</guid><description>Custom Post Types (CPT) in Wordpress are just like blog posts, except that you can manipulate them to make them correspond to any type of publication you want.
For example, let’s say that you have a website where you publish movie reviews. In this case, instead of using the default post type of “blog post” you can create a CPT with the name of movie review.
This post type would probably have other fields, other than content and thumbnail.</description></item><item><title>How to display Recent posts in Wordpress</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/05-display-posts/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/05-display-posts/</guid><description>When working within the Wordpress framework you will soon be confronted with the necessity of displaying the posts that are saved in your database. Be it for an archive page or because you want to display your latest posts in your homepage.
Remember that when I talk about Wordpress posts, I do not necessarily mean that we are talking about a conventional blog. Wordpress has grown to be more than a blogging platform.</description></item><item><title>How to create short-codes in Wordpress</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/04-shortcodes/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/04-shortcodes/</guid><description>Short-codes are one of the signatures of Wordpress. They allow you to add functionalities to your website by just adding a few characters in the following format: [my-shortcode].
Sometimes, you will be asked to add them to your website by some plugins.
For example, WP Forms provides you with a custom short-code like this one: [wpforms id=&amp;quot;25”] for each form that you build using your plugin. You will then add this anywhere you want your form to appear.</description></item><item><title>How to add a favicon to your Wordpress website</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/03-favicons/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/03-favicons/</guid><description>There are better and worse ways to add a favicon to your Wordpress website. In regular websites, all you would need to do to add a favicon is to add the following tag to your header:
&amp;lt;link rel=&amp;#34;icon&amp;#34; href=&amp;#34;url-of-your-favicon.ico&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; We could, of course, just plug this tag to our website’s header. But that wouldn’t be the Wordpress way of doing things.
How to add a favicon the Wordpress way The better way of doing this in Wordpress is by adding it to our Wordpress cycle.</description></item><item><title>How to enqueue styles and scripts in Wordpress</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/02-enqueing-styles-and-scripts/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/02-enqueing-styles-and-scripts/</guid><description>How to enqueue scripts and styles in Wordpress As you might know, when we are using Wordpress, we don’t add our scripts and styles directly in the header like this:
&amp;lt;script src=&amp;#34;my_script.js&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt; Of course, you can do it that way, but there is another way, the right way.
The right way to add any dependencies on Wordpress, be it scripts or stylesheets, is to enqueue them in the Wordpress cycle. The reason for this is that Wordpress itself includes different scripts and stylesheets when it loads.</description></item><item><title>How to create a child theme in Wordpress with code</title><link>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/01-how-to-create-a-child-theme/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aavila0707.github.io/posts/wordpress/01-how-to-create-a-child-theme/</guid><description>Creating a child-theme in Wordpress is extremely useful. It allows you to modify your theme while still getting updates to that theme.
What is a child-theme in Wordpress? Imagine you have a very nice theme, but you would like to add a certain feature that does not come with it by default.
An intuitive approach could be to go to your theme files and add the feature yourself. But if you did that, any update to your theme would erase your custom feature.</description></item></channel></rss>